okay let's
meditate watch your
breath e
just a breath just one thing meditation
means just one
thing e
come to the golden MO
see the sky blue
see the
mountains across the valley
come back to the
room sit with your
teacher
e e
and look at their eyes
sure try to have a personal experience
of your three friends let's start with
can you
identify can you isolate the part of
your mind Shing which catches you being
distracted
your awareness that you're not on the
object or that the object is not clear
can you isolate your frame called
Juma your ability to bring the Mind back
to the
object so fast almost instantaneous can
you can you catch yourself bringing your
mind back to the object
and then your third
friend the
enjoyment of the object
the
contentment with it so deep that you
could stay with it forever you could
stay with it for an hour or two hours
you wouldn't feel like leaving the
object deep enjoyment and pleasure in
the object if you can get to
Nar you've bypassed the elephant and the
monkey e
watch your contentment be aware of your
contentment and stay with the
object take sustenance from the
contentment that's the real food of
meditation that sustains your mind and
body feel like you're feeding on that
feeling of contentment and
presence e
come back slowly to the
room okay back to some
emptiness he's still talking
about uh
how the G is under your nose the gacha
is under your nose all the time and
uh if we
could really if you could just have
someone sit there with you with the pen
for a few
minutes uh you would see the gaka and
then it wouldn't be such a problem right
uh but people have wandered among the
classical text for years of their lives
you know trying to grasp the GTA and
it's and he's still making the point
that is it's under your nose all the
time it's right in front of you all the
time so here we
go suppose you are able to really
identify what the gagcha is okay just
once let's go over gagcha
okay gacha is a pen that's not there or
Nick is easier where's Nick yeah you're
easier uh there's a Nick that's there he
raised his hand he has a nice smile you
know he worked really hard and build
some of cabin single-handedly pretty
much and
uh you know he's there that Nick is
there then
uh if he gets accused of stealing the
books from the bookstore right wrongly
right then uh it's an unjust we talked
about unjust accusation and then we said
there's no such thing right whatever if
someone accuses you of something it's
because you you did it to someone else
before life is made of perfect Justice
okay you can either suffer from that or
or you use it to get the things you want
you know
so try to try to think if you're close
to him you can look at him uh try to
think of him
as as the Nick who doesn't deserve to be
blamed all right try to picture sitting
there the spiritual
gangster
who doesn't deserve to be blamed when
he's blamed got it where is that
Nick where's that
Nick doesn't exist okay there's no such
Nick okay the Nick who got
blamed when he didn't deserve to be
blamed there's no such Nick okay you
comfortable with that because we deserve
everything that happens to us right
because the
person uh coming in your fa what do you
call it you can't say this is
frustrating uh the person who's in your
face blaming you it's coming directly
from seeds in your own mind right so if
we tried really hard to look over there
where Nick is and try to picture a Nick
who didn't deserve the blame he got
blamed we would come up with zero okay
he's not that Nick is not there there is
a Nick which is there which is the Nick
who's sitting there and helped build a
house and all that okay that Nick is
there but the Nick who didn't deserve to
be blamed when he got blamed that Nick's
not there okay that Nick is the gaka all
right comfortable that's a Nick which
isn't there it's a Nick which never was
there it's a Nick which never will be
there it's a Nick which could not
possibly be there ever past present or
future never will be never could be the
Nick who didn't deserve to get blamed
when he got blamed okay all right so
when you're looking for G it's a little
tricky right because you're looking for
something that couldn't exist anyway I
like to call it the two-headed
purple elephant two-headed 17 foot
purple elephant rampaging through this
room at this very moment right is there
an elephant in this room right now I
mean a real
elephant I mean nobody looked around
right it it's big it would be big you
would have seen it okay
uh but that's not gacha okay the absence
of elephant in this room is an existing
thing
okay the absence of an Indian Elephant
in this room is an existing object there
is an absence of elephant in this room
that absence truly exists
okay but but the gaka is more radical
the gaka is let's discuss
whether Obama and his twin brother are
here right now okay and Obama doesn't
have a twin brother that I know of okay
so you're asking does a thing which
doesn't exist
is a thing which doesn't exist here in
the room with us you see when you're
looking for a
gaka it's more radical than something
that's not here cuz an elephant cannot
be here and that's okay elephants exist
you could have an elephant in here but
there just doesn't happen to be one here
gcha is more radical is is there a
two-headed purple elephant 17t High
rampaging to this room then you say no
and nobody even looked around
right because it couldn't be because
they don't exist they just don't exist
right when we're looking for a
Nick there's a Nick which does exist
which is the one who's sitting there
nodding and smiling and then there's a
Nick that doesn't exist which is the one
who didn't deserve to get blame because
everybody deserves everything that
happens to them
okay so there's a real example of gaka
okay but when Nick is blamed under
pressure you know when someone's in your
face blaming you and there's an emotion
that comes up and you feel angry then
the the invisible impossible Nick gets
really big to especially to
Nick okay like how could he blame me you
know I didn't do it so there's two
there's even two Nicks there two extra
Nicks that don't exist you know I didn't
do it that Nick and why is he blaming me
okay those two Nicks aren't there all
right but they get really big when
you're
upset okay those those get really big
when you're upset right okay so then he
says gaka if you're able to just grasp
what a gcha would be like we have to say
it that way way right you can't say what
the gaka
is because they don't exist you have to
say what the G I have people send me
Buddhist translations or Buddhist
writing
by you know modern Scholars I open it up
at any page it says the gcha
is I just throw it away I've never
gotten through one of them okay I can't
say that there's no such thing you see
you have to say if the gaka
existed conditional tense there's no
such thing right if it existed then what
would it be like okay it would be a Nick
who who didn't deserve to be blamed okay
so if you can identify what the gcha
would be okay what the
gcha okay would be CH then if someone
comes up with you with some proof of BU
of emptiness right and they say
uh you can say take a a plant take one
of these trees out here
uh it's
empty because it's dependently
originating okay some that's a classical
proof for emptiness okay if you've
already grasped what the gaka
is could be
uh then
you then you then all those Buddhist uh
proofs are easy for you you see you can
struggle through all the Buddhist proofs
there's like 20 30 of them for emptiness
or you could just understand the gaka of
Nick or the go have a pen then go back
to those 20 or 30 proofs and they're
just C piece of cake cuz they're all the
same okay so here we
go then you can use those Buddhist
reasonings you can learn them and then
he says you can take the mountain of
your misunderstanding of your world and
reduce it to dust I like it okay you can
take the mountain of your
misunderstanding of Your World and
reduce it to dust okay tell
Lo s really beautiful I forget what that
is B kururu Basu what's basma basma is
that uh when you burn a dead body in bar
and you get BMA but it means dust tiny
pieces of Ash so in Sanskrit the word
for that is like
giri smash the mountain to to to smaller
than dust to powder is that that powder
you use on your head like that basma
okay I love that
[Music]
word then you wouldn't have any trouble
seeing is a little
tricky it's very very colloquial and it
would mean something like
uh I want to get a nice English one
okay you pretty much wouldn't have any
trouble
seeing okay you pretty much wouldn't
have any problem
seeing that's a
m pretty much
mean you might have okay he's like
hedging his his BS there you pretty much
really have any
trouble yeah right okay
also said so isting got
it very beautiful okay uh you can break
silence
ready okay go back to silence right
uh says you don't got to look for the
gaka the gaka is the person looking for
the gaka
okay you don't got to look for the Goa
the gaka is the person looking for the
you don't have to go any further than
the person looking for the
G it's beautiful right very sexy okay
that's my kind of sexy
anyway you don't got to go looking far
away for the
it is cohabitating with the with the
looker the Tibetan means it's
cohabitating with the looker wherever
the looker for the gcha goes the gcha
like you go to sleep the gcha goes to
sleep you have breakfast the having
breakfast okay you are Co what do you
call you can't say all right I gotta
find all my own words now
end a big section we just ended a big
section um
therefore you could spend years months
years or months of your life just
devoted to trying to find the gcha and
that would be a good use of your
time just if you want to see emptiness
start with just getting clear on what
the gcha is try to get good at
identifying the gchas in your life
they will be more pronounced when you're
under pressure someone's blaming you or
someone's criticizing
you or when you want something really
bad right let's explore
that let's explore that uh so you really
like uh Maple covered Donuts okay let's
say you really like Maple covered
donuts and then uh there's only one left
in the cafeteria and then you hit the
door at the same time as somebody else
who hits the door that you know who
really
likes cover Donuts okay like you both
hit the door at the same time
right if you rush forward to grasp the
last Maple covered
donut you must by definition be grasping
the
gaka okay under the influence of
Desire
uh you can't think straight a donut
which you could get by being the first
one
there doesn't
exist all right but under the what they
call there's a Celtic
word glamour they call it glamour
glamour in Celtic means uh like a magic
spell under the spell of
under the spell of desire for the donut
you you rush to get to it first okay the
Donate you're rushing to get to First
doesn't even exist okay that's gaka that
donut is gcha a donut you could get by
getting a donut first doesn't exist okay
all Donuts you ever got in your life
assuming they tasted good to you okay be
careful there assuming they were tasted
good to you have come from sharing the
donuts you liked with other people okay
that's the only way to get a donut okay
when you look at a
donut and you think you're you're a real
Buddhist what do you
call Glutton okay an enlightened Glutton
like me okay and then I like that that's
the name of my next album uh the
enlightened Glutton okay so so you look
at the donnut and because you want it so
much you split it with everybody in the
room and I do that right because I'm
enlightened Glutton I want more Donuts
okay I like donuts so I I share it with
everybody just as a matter of now it's a
matter of habit you know uh
so when I look at a
donut and because I wanted with an
enlightened wanting
decide to share it is that a gaka is
that Don a
gaka no it's the opposite that's a real
donut because I
am I'm acknowledging the fact that I can
only get it by sharing that kind of
donut exists on the table okay that kind
of donut exists on the table the same
object if I approach it with the feeling
that I got to get to it first for me to
get it that same object becomes a
phantom and it doesn't exist okay that
that donut doesn't exist okay it's very
tricky right it's very tricky in any
given donut there's two
Donuts in any given pen we said
yesterday there's two pens there's one
that doesn't exist there's one that does
exist and the one that doesn't exist
causes you all your suffering you grab
for the gcha donut you take it home you
eat the Gchat donut and then your karma
to have a donut is exhausted and you
don't get a donut next time okay which
is dumb okay so gas causes all our
trouble and if you can good at weeding
out gust from real things you got to get
good at weeding out the gust from the
real things okay then you're then your
life is successful and happy and
enlightened you can have everything you
want I pretty much have everything I
want you
know uh to the extent that I don't it's
because I I'm still grabbing G okay all
right so he says it would be worth weeks
or months or years of your life just to
find the gcha just to identify the gcha
okay and the
barometer for a gcha is how upset or
craving you
feel okay that when you feel upset or
when you feel craving I distinguish
between craving and wanting it's fine to
want a donut it's wrong to crave a donut
craving means you eat two or three or
four or five you eat the whole bag of
potato all right wanting is like you
open up the bag you take out one or two
you eat them you enjoy them that's okay
right to the extent that you have
compulsive eating to the extent that you
feel angry or upset at the people around
you you are swimming in G
cuz you can't feel upset or angry and
you can't want to eat compulsively if
you understand the
thing it's not possible so anytime
you're screwed up
emotionally you're swimming in go okay
it's must say that here somewhere okay
uh okay that was the first of four
crucial points that were used to analyze
the fact that Mike doesn't have a self
Mike is not Mike let's put it that way
rather than saying Mike has no
self I think it's clearer in English to
say Mike is not mine okay and they that
it's what it means that's what no self
means Mike is not mine okay for me to
understand that Mike is not Mike it will
take four four subjects right four
things we have to discuss we just
finished the first one it was long it
was called gaka the gaka of mic okay
identifying the mic that isn't there
okay we finished
that now we have to go to another
question which is uh
how what do you call it how pervasive is
the gaka how pervasive is the gaka how
far does the gcha go is everything a
gcha no Nick over there looking at me
like uh or smiling uh that Nick exists
the Nick that got blamed
wrongly doesn't exist so we have to get
good
at identifying the breadth of the gaka
you see I mean how how far does it go
and where does it doesn't go where does
it not go gaka doesn't reach to the Nick
over there it's sitting there but it
does reach the Nick who shouldn't have
got blamed didn't deserve to get blamed
all right so it's difficult to to cut
the borders to
demarcate the borders of Paka it's
difficult okay so that's our next
subject what is the breadth of the gaka
okay how far does it extend and where
does it not extend
okay
uh if you're able to pick up a pan or a
donut
right and immediately strip off the G
donut you know if you're that good at
it what again what is the gagcha donut
the one that if you got to First you
could have
it because such a thing doesn't
exist but you got to strip that off the
donut which is there which you can pick
up and chew because of your past Karma
that you shared Don okay there the same
donut that's a problem
okay if you get it straight in your mind
and you can you can put your mind on the
easily
right then you can then we start an
exercise okay very difficult exercise it
has been mistaught for thousands of
years over the years I mean some people
taught it right some people didn't teach
it right so it's pretty muddled Now by
by now it's pretty muddled all right
let's go for
it is this a pen you can just
nod
uh is it coming this way or is it coming
this way you can just wave your hand
yeah it's coming this way
okay is there a pen which seems to be
coming this way to to a normal person
you could say yeah there is a pen with
seems to be coming this way there's a a
phantom or an apparition or an
appearance of a pen that seems to be
coming this way okay try to grasp on to
that that one try to isolate that one in
your
mind the a pen which comes from
itself a pen which comes from itself
it's just an imaginary thing it's like
the two-headed purple elephant it has as
much existence as a two-headed purple
elant it doesn't exist but you can
imagine it right you can imagine things
that don't exist that doesn't make them
real it makes the imagination real
okay so try to hold your mind on the pen
that that's not
there or that you could say the pen that
you could
buy the pen that you got by buying it is
there such a pen No Such Thing you only
get pens by giving them to others that's
the only way to get a pen but that's not
right gy Michael I went and bought a pen
if you go to a store and they have pens
do you always get
them no sometimes you don't have money
if you have money and you go to a store
well you always get a pen no they don't
come from money okay all right I mean
that's a it sounds like a dumb proof but
it's a total absolute proof
okay
uh put your mind on the pen that you got
from buying it where where is it be
careful where is it
put your mind on the pen that you got
from purchasing it or the pen that was
made in a factory where where is that
pen just point to it it's okay yeah NY
were like this okay I can only imagine
it you see it doesn't exist it doesn't
exist I can imagine it but it doesn't
exist where's the two-headed purple
out yeah you can only go like this it's
just in your imagination it does exist
there but not in a real sense like it
can't Gore you or something
okay
uh now consider the parts of this pen
okay top Barrel what do you call thing
inside no you can't say right uh anyway
that thing that holds the ink okay
uh I didn't hear you anyway it's okay
uh now grasp this and okay grasp this
and we can make it through the next five
pages or so and I dare say there are
very few monks who who have ever made it
through the next five pages okay but you
can do it cuz you got it already
Okay consider all the parts of this
pen what's the relationship between all
those parts and the pen that you could
purchase in a
store I I didn't ask where are they the
parts are here the parts are out here
okay the pen that you could purchase in
your store is where in your hand what's
the relationship between the
two okay we have to talk we have to
discuss uh we have to discuss the idea
of relationship okay and it's a
fundamental principle of all logic that
for two things to have a relationship
they must both exist
right they must both exist I mean that's
just basic okay there if you want to
know what you didn't but I'm going to
tell you anyway there's only two
possible relationships one is uh a
possession you know the top of the
pen and when is
identity uh the black cylinder and the
pen okay
uh but in either case the two elements
that have the chair relationship must
both exist okay you can't talk
about uh the relationship between this
book and the two-headed purple elephant
in this room okay cuz one of them
doesn't exist you can't have a tie a
rope between two things that one of them
okay so now I I'll ask you again and now
you'll give me a better
answer what's the
relationship between all the parts of
this pen and you can even say the the
whole what do you call it
the the whole right what's I you can
either say parts or you can say the the
sum of the parts you can either say the
individual parts or you can say the sum
of the parts but what's the relationship
between the parts and the sum of the
parts and that pen that I bought in a
store no Rel it cannot be a relationship
okay it can't have a relationship cu the
second one doesn't exist
you can't find a pen that you bought in
a store all pens that ever I should
rather say a pen that came to you
because you bought it in a store that
doesn't exist there's no such thing pens
only come to you because you share pens
with others okay that's why you can go
to the store and not get the pen you
want when you have the
money it's so simple okay the
explanation for human failure over the
last 50,000 years is rather simple okay
we just have to stop doing it okay then
you everything you do is successful okay
it's cool so if you understand that we
can go on all right then we can
discuss whether the pen that was never
there is is the whole the sum of the
parts or the parts
okay got
it is the pen that was never
there in the parts or in the some of the
part he's Diamond dealing you
honey okay you want the black diamond or
the yellow one okay yeah you got to say
I'm not buying it I'm not buying it the
pen that was never there is neither in
the parts of the pen nor is it even in
the sum of the parts of the pen it just
ain't there okay you just understood the
next five pages okay and very few monks
understand it okay got it they go off on
these weird things and they get really
confused okay but you got it okay
is now uh be careful okay this is
Buddhist debate okay be careful is there
a pen here does a pen exist
here is the pen which really does exist
here okay it does exist here there is a
pen here if you don't believe me come up
get your Saddam Hussein mustach okay uh
is the pen which exists here does it
have a relationship to its
parts yeah it must have some
relationship to its parts you take away
the parts you can't write anything there
must be a relationship okay we can say
that the whole pen depends on its parts
the sum of the parts is the pen we can
say
that but the pen which is not coming
from me the pen which is not coming from
my kindness to other people
okay is it the parts of the pen or is it
the sum of the parts of the pen then you
just got to go like that I'm not buying
that one I'm not buying that one I don't
want the other Diamond I want the black
one give me the white one give me the D
Flawless okay what is the D Flawless of
pens yeah there's a pen that depends on
its part but it's the pen that I have
synthesized from the seeds in my own
mind which were planted there when I
show proferred kindness to other people
in some way with a pen okay that pen is
that's the def Flawless pen that pen
exists that pen that's the only pen that
ever was there the pen which has come
from your kindness is the only pen that
ever was there okay and the only thing
holding up this
ceiling I like I like this thing I when
I rewrite science I'm going to use this
um science is like 90% cool it just
needs a little tweaking okay I'm not
kidding that's my next
project but you you consider the the
structural beams right the structural
pillars which are helping to hold up
that they're kind of cute
right which are holding up the roof okay
they are holding up the roof right and
then you ask anybody engineer what's
what is it in the wood that's holding up
the roof
and they'll say there's some what do you
call
it structural strength right uh tensile
strength of the wood the atoms of the
wood are aligned in such a way that
there's a tensile strength along that
angle which allows it to hold up the
roof if that tensile strength goes under
the strength required to hold up that
much weight then the roof will fall
that's that's how we in our world Planet
a that's how we understand roofs falling
down okay but what lends the tensile
strength to the wood what why did that
would have that strength who put it
there you see your kindness your
kindness okay you you supported someone
else you you housed another person who
needed housing okay some people came to
some people from di Mountain came to
Grub your spare bedroom for the next six
years and uh
and you put up with it
happily
uh and then that creates in your mind a
seed to perceive tensile strength into
the wood okay that's where the tensile
strength came from so we can reasonably
say in a future Planet a that the the
force which is holding up the building
is not the atomic structure of the
elements in the wood it's the kindness
you have shown to others and then you
you get some thrill up your spine right
they say a person who really gets it
they feel this shiver up their spine
right now you know like ooh yeah what if
kindness were holding up everything you
know what if all physical support of all
physical things was was was the product
of kindness towards others then then
what kind of world would we have what if
people understood that you know then you
never have a roof fall
down for example okay but basically
everybody be nice to everybody it's
prettier which is pretty awesome I think
okay you'd have to
be remember that okay I I think that's
so remember the kindness thing okay all
right it's also putting the power into
your food and into your medicines it's
what drives your car gasoline doesn't
drive a car these are profound things if
the world
comes to understand them the world will
become a paradise okay all right and
that's what we're doing every we're blah
blah blah blah that's uh we're offering
that paradise that was created when
everybody got it okay here we
go yeah so he says
look the way the way Pabon chooses to
teach the concept of the
comprehensiveness of the gaka how far
does the gaka go the way he chooses to
teach it
is through what we just said is the is
the pen which doesn't exist Does that
lie within its parts or does it lie
within the sum of its parts okay that's
how he interprets the
word uh how comprehensive is the gaka
okay all right
if the pen which was not coming from
your kindness existed can we reasonably
say that it must either be in the parts
of the pen or in the sum of the parts of
the pen can we say that have we covered
all possibilities I'll say it
again if the pen which wasn't coming
from our kindness how much does that pen
exist zero but if it did
exist can we say it would either be in
its part or in the sum of its part or is
there a third possibility is there a
Pumba see could could anything in the
world which
exists not be either its parts or the
sum of its
part can we say that I'll say it again
you guys had too much lunch I I knew
that was going to
happen if a thing exists can we say it
is either its parts or is either the sum
of its parts and no other is possible
it's
okay
okay if if G Michael exists can we say
he's either the Su of his parts or he's
one of his Parts can we say that you
could say that which one does he happen
to be the gim Michel does exist happens
to be the sum of his Parts okay all
right especially if you throw in that
part about him coming from your seat all
right
all he's trying to say is if we were
going to explore the existence of a
thing we could look for it in its parts
or we could look for it in the sum of
its parts and if we didn't find it in
either one we could conclusively
say it didn't exist that's all okay got
it it's got to be one or the other now
that got lazy sized I just made a new
verse that got
lised that got lzed in modern Tibetan
Buddhist Monastery okay now they just
say one or many self-existent one or
many you know it's either one everything
in the world has to be either one or or
many the two clocks are many the one
clock is one everything in the
world has to be either singular or
plural can we say that everything in the
world is either singular or plural can
we say that so if we take any particular
object and examine it to see whether
it's one and we say and we decide it's
not one and then we examine it to see if
it's plural and we decide it's not
plural can we say it doesn't
exist yeah cuz that's the only two
possibilities that's
all okay that's all we're just trying to
find two possibilities now it got lzed
in modern Tibetan monasteries they
discuss it that way is the clock
one from its own side no is the clock to
from its own time no so the clock
doesn't exist from its own time CU all
everything has to be either one or
plural that's all that's the way they
they say it nowadays but it was more
difficult in old days it was
harder what's the relationship between a
real pen and its parts is it its parts
individually or is it the sum of its
parts it's a sum of its parts okay the
pen is not the top of the pen right pen
is not the tip of the pen the pen is all
the parts put together the pen is the
sum of the
part so if we wanted to determine
whether something were a pen all right
stay with me if we wanted to determine
if something were a
pen could we check two in two places
could we say either it's it's Parts
individually or it's all of the parts of
a pen together can we say that and if
it's not either one of those we can
safely say it's not a pen okay that's
all they say you have a house you're a
Tibetan farmer you have a house it only
has two rooms okay you have one goat the
goat has wandered into the house all
right or someone said the goat I saw the
goat wander into the house so you check
one room leaving it you lock the doors
and windows okay then you go to the
other room check the second room the
goat's not there all right can we say
then the goat is not in the house yes
cuz there's only two rooms all right in
the house and he's not the goat's not in
the first room the ghost not in the
second room and you locked the first one
so he couldn't have gotten into the
first one from the second one like
around the back or all right okay okay
does the Nick who got wrongly blamed for
stealing the bgs and the like there's
some seed being formed now I'm
sorry that's the Nick who got wrong and
he blame you know blah blah is he his
ear or his arm or his leg individually
no now here's the hard one is the Nick
who got wrongly blamed for studying the
books the sum of all the parts of Nick
to G no is there any other possibility
to find the Nick who got blamed wrongly
somewhere else
like in her parts or in her Parts you
know can you say we could look somewhere
else no there's only two rooms okay
there's only Nick's parts or or the
collection of Ni Parts okay got it
that's all if you get that we can go on
if we had any
time uh
no let's do some meditation cuz you got
it I just want you to rest a bit you go
to the golden room and rest a bit
okay by the way the parts thing is the
plural thing and the sum of the this the
sum total is the one thing and that's
the way it used to be explain and then
it got simplified into one or many okay
you got that yeah okay here we
go watch your
breath e
breath is the only thing in the world
even Nick's not there anymore just a
breath
check the corners of your mouth for
tension check your forehead for tension
check
the upper eyelids for tension and
release it
come to that beautiful golden
room start to go into your contentment
even
now and you can skip
the agitation and the dullness from the
beginning be happy and content to be in
the golden room even before your teacher
comes
with some sense of anticipation
look out at the Blue
Sky enjoy the sky
let your eyes drop from the sky to the
mountains in the valley that separates
you in the
mountains e
and come into the golden
room and request your teacher to come
the Colden sunlight is coming to the
windows and is warm on your body and
it's warm on their
body warm on and liquid gold right
just sit with them quietly doing
nothing and feel the warmth of the gold
sunlight on your body
every once in a while use
your every once in a while use your sh
to check in on your
n do you still feel contented and happy
in the
room e
you still feeling
n I'm your
s e
stay happy contented no need to move
come slowly back to the seat
relax and open your
eyes uh I think without noticing it
you're up to 15 minutes of high quality
meditation you see get the quality first
and then the and then the time will come
you can do an now but but work on the
quality first then the hour comes
naturally all right we have about
another 15 minutes I would let you ask
questions but you can't if you want to
write questions before the evening
sessions about today's class I'll answer
those okay and I have questions from
last night about or this morning about
meditation questions so we'll cover
those both uh in the evening class okay
I suppose 3:30 right
[Music]
yeah
good
uh if if the
let's say if the Nick who were unjustly
blamed
okay if
he if he existed then he should either
be his Parts separately or the some
total of his Parts can we say that no
other choice PBA there's Pumba used in a
scripture okay we uh often use the word
Pumba at diamond mountain or other
places to to describe a a third
possibility uh PBA means a third a third
choice so normally people are normally
people confront themselves with two
untenable choices and then we encourage
them say in a business setting we
encourage them to think of a of an
unexpected solution which would be
called a pmba or a third a third
alternative okay so here it is used in a
scripture
um is there a Pumba between
if Nick existed he would either have to
be his ear or his arm or his leg or he'd
have to be the sum total of all those
parts is there a third possibility like
could he be her her arms and
ears is there a Pumba you have to say no
okay there's no there's no other option
you could say other option okay either
he's either he's his Parts individually
or he's the sum total of his Parts cuz
it' be ridiculous to say that he was
Miriam's parts or something like that
it'd be ridiculous to go searching
elsewhere in someone else's eyes and
ears and you know
okay not
possible generally speaking every object
that exists in the in the universe
should either be singular or
plural okay what about
shoes H that's mean
okay uh
[Music]
pants if it's generally true that
everything in the world should be either
singular or
plural uh then it should be true okay
now here's a new he's throwing in a new
thing all right
if if
Nick uh existed from his own side okay
if Nick existed from his own side and if
he wasn't if my perception of him wasn't
coming from me okay if he existed
somehow from his own
side then can we say that due to his
relationship with his
parts then his arm should also exist
from its own side and his ear should
also exist from its own side can we say
that
yeah you can right so if you know if his
head were I'm sorry if Nick was a
two-headed purple elephant because we're
talking impossibilities right you got to
appreciate that you got to stay there if
Nick were a two-headed purple elephant
then Nick's arm would be a two-headed
purple okay if Nick were coming from his
own side then his arm would also be
coming from his own side it's the same
statement okay just a second one feels
more comfortable okay because he's not
purple
okay decide that it's that's the way it
is it wouldn't be reasonable to say that
uh if Nick were coming from his own side
then his Parts wouldn't be coming from
the okay we would have to say if Nick
were coming from his own side then the
parts of Nick would have to be coming
from their own side okay we could also
say that if Nick were coming from his
own side there'd either have to be one
Nick coming from his own side or
multiple Nicks coming from his own side
because everything is either one or many
okay except for shoes I don't know don't
worry about
[Music]
that women you can really confuse some
young monk in the monastery in the
debate ground you throw the shoes thing
out him and he just walk away and he's
just sitting there
like
okay Nick were coming from his own side
then Nick would either have to be one
thing that was coming from his own side
or multiple things that was coming from
his own side can we say that if we
determined that he was
neither could we say that he wasn't
coming from his own side that's all
that's all and you can do that with
anything okay you can do that with
anything inequality in the world you can
say uh everything that's blue and
everything that's not blue or you could
say everything that's called and
everything that's not called or you
could say everything that's my the
bunion on my left foot and everything
that's not the bunion on my left foot
then you examine them both you go to the
two rooms to see if the goat is there
that's all you go to the bunion and you
check if it's coming from its own side
you say no then you check everything
that's not the bunion and see if they're
coming from your own side you say no
then you can say nothing comes from its
own side that's right it's just an
artificial you can use any division you
want it doesn't matter you can use
bunions you can use Sky you can use
Parts okay that's all multiple singular
doesn't matter you can use anything okay
uh okay
we do that
again he says you have to chew on these
ideas means not for a day or two but
uh until you like feel really confident
about these ideas you can't chew on them
for a day or two and go back to
Cincinnati and forget about it and
expect to make progress you're going to
have to chew on these
thoughts uh for a long
time and again you got to be like do you
know in Tibet they say a
goose I think it's a goose a goose has
the capacity to take a bowl in which you
have poured by we lost the pen uh in
which you have don't worry don't worry
no then don't look for it you won't find
it
or is it a I think it's a peacock I'm
not sure
anyway by tradition there's an animal
which can take a bowl of milk and water
what it is it peacock and then yeah it's
a peacock and then they can separate out
they can drink all the milk and leave
the water somehow okay so we have to do
the same thing like now for the rest of
your life uh you have to approach
objects like Maple covered Donuts or NX
nixes and then uh you have to look at
and say what's what part of this guy
doesn't exist and what part of this guy
does exist okay what part of this guy
doesn't exist the Nick who is friendly
from his own side doesn't exist either
okay he is friendly if you like that
he's friendly then you got to sustain
that friendliness by being friendly to
others that's all so approach Nick with
knowledge you know I like Nick he's
friendly well then gosh you better be
you better be friendly to people more or
else he'll stop being friendly got it
cuz it'll wear out all seeds wear out
right that's all if you approach and
then if you approach Nick he's mean to
you and you want to say something back
to him you can
stop because saying something back to
him is what made him mean in the first
place right so don't don't don't ever
engage in a relationship with a Nick
that's not there
because you'll have trouble there there
will be trouble okay the Nick who's mean
to me not because I was mean to others
doesn't exist and there's no good way
you can relate to the mik is mean niku
is mean to you not because you were mean
to others got it you can't have any
meaningful relationship with the Nick
who's mean to you not because you were
mean to others CU that Nick don't exist
okay and then if you try to have a
relationship with that Nick you're going
to have trouble and that's what happens
people are having trying to have a
relationship with a phantom it does
that's what Maya means that's what
illusion means okay you want to know
illusion and Maya and all that
crap uh it's uh it's try to have a
relationship try to relate try to relate
to the Nick who's mean to you not
because you were mean to others okay and
then you get into choices and dis
decisions should I try to negotiate with
him or should I just punch him you know
no and your your whole life is taken up
by choosing between two options which
are both untenable because he doesn't
exist you're punching someone who
doesn't exist and you're negotiating
with someone who doesn't exist when
you're trying to talk him out of being
mean to you or you're trying to show
that you you're not going to take it you
know in each case you're relating to a
thing that doesn't exist you are showing
who that that you're not going to take
it a two-headed purple outfit and who is
it that you're going to reason with so
he does not mean to you anymore do that
in purple elephant so stop reasoning
with him stop punching him stop thinking
those are the only two
options and start being nice to other
people and then he won't be mean to you
anymore and then you don't have to worry
about whether you're negotiate with him
or punch him because they don't work
okay they just don't work they don't
work because they don't always work
rather we should say they don't work
because they never did work
when they did seem to work it was
something else going on okay all right
and that's a pretty good place to stop
I'd say but then
again let's get all the time you know
God to get us all in one place and uh
not not dead from pneumonia yet and
still able to hear it's pretty rare
let's let's take a couple more minutes
threw in a nasty thing he was mean I
should I even tell
you no it's too confusing
later yeah okay so we're going on to the
third of the four crucial points okay
the first one was what identifying who's
the Nick who's not there and we finished
that okay the Nick who was mean to me
not because I was mean to others ain't
there that's the gaka Nick okay the Nick
who's mean to
me is there got it the Nick was mean to
me is there that's the water the Nick
was mean to me not because I was mean to
others is not there and that's the milk
and can you divide them in any given
stressful situation okay cuz you'll have
to all right then the second one was
look if
he's if that Nick existed he'd either
have to be Nick's parts or it have to be
Nick the sum of Nick's Parts okay and we
decided there's only two rooms to look
for the go okay third
one the third crucial point is where you
go to the one room and you and
you conclusively determine that the
the Nick who's mean not because I was
mean to others is not
plural then you're going to then the
fourth point is going to be you're going
to go to the other room and look for the
Nick who's mean to you not because you
were mean to others and decide that he's
not single a single thing okay wait
sorry the single one goes first and the
plural one goes second so if the Nick
who's mean to me not because I was mean
to others EX existed he'd have to be in
either room he'd either have to be one
thing or he'd have to be many things
okay and it's just obvious that it's one
thing okay it's not two Nicks all right
but this is just a way that you could
set bunion and non bunion it doesn't
matter
okay if the Nick who's mean to me not
because I was mean to others existed
he'd either have to be one Nick like
that or he'd have to be two Nicks like
that okay then I'm going to check each
possibility that's the next two
Parts okay we'll just do a little bit
is is Mike singular or plural you can't
say right you can go yeah Mike is
singular you don't say Mike's okay uh
Mike is singular
[Music]
and the gcha mic is singular from his
own side can we say
that Mike Mike Mike is singular can we
say
that uh can we say if the mic that
doesn't exist did exist he'd have to be
singular can we say that okay
good the
mic that we grab on to
the the pens that you ever saw in your
life so far were they real did you think
they were real they you did think they
were real and they were real
okay if a thing were really singular
would it always appear to be
singular yeah I mean that's what real
implies okay real implies that it is the
way it appears okay so can we say that
uh if Mike was just one he should always
appear as one especially if he were
existing on his own side okay all right
I mean it gets kind of weird right if I
was a two-headed purple elepant you know
should I have snot in my in my trunk or
not you know I mean the whole discussion
gets a little weird okay cuz the thing
doesn't exist got it but if if the M if
the if the Nick that was mean not
because I was mean to others existed uh
would he be one and you'd say yes cuz
there's only one new but then the next
question is would he appear to be one to
us and you'd have to say yes because
we're dealing with the impossibility of
a thing which comes from its own side
and is not subjective it's objective
okay if he were one he'd have to appear
to be one and not many okay because he's
real that's what real means real means
and we'll stop there okay I'm going to
throw the meaning of real at you and
then uh and then we'll stop there
because you can digest it along with
your dinner or comes after
that oh we do a meditation thing after
that
okay here we go the test of a Thing If a
thing is real or
not in in Buddhist philosophy is
that does
it exist in the way that it
appears does the way it appears and the
way it is do those two things match or
not that's all that's the test of
reality in Buddhism okay when you take
the example of a mirage okay on the road
what do they call those things Mirage on
the on this road from a distance
uh the appearance is of
water the reality is is of asphalt okay
do they match then that's that's a test
of the reality of the of the Mirage okay
if the way it appears doesn't match the
way it is then we can say it's not
real the leaf that crossed the road in h
New Jersey in 1976 or something and
uh and the appearance of a mouth it
appeared to be a
mouth it was a
leaf uh was it a real mouth see then you
say no cuz the appearance and the
reality didn't match that's
okay so the test of reality just I'm
going to leave you with that the test of
whether a thing is real or not is
whether its appearance matches the way
it is
okay it it appears that a Nick who is
mean to you is being mean to you because
he wants to be mean to you and no other
reason uh the fact is that he's being
mean to you because you've been mean to
others okay so can we say that to to
most people that meanness is sort of a
loser you see the way it seems to be and
the way it really is don't match so can
we say that for most people they are
living in a world of Illusion you see
that there's an unreality there the what
they're seeing and what's there don't
match they're seeing a nikus mean
because he wants to be mean but the
reality is that he's mean because I was
mean to somebody else in the past and
those don't match therefore that the
Nick that I'm holding to be mean to me
when I misunderstand Nick is an illusion
and it's not real okay that's a that's a
test of a thing's unreality okay it's
not
real and then to try to interact with
unreal things is is just frustrating
okay trying to get a car to start trying
to get your boyfriend to to act the way
you want you know this don't it's not
going to happen
because they're not real the boyfriend
you're dealing with is not real the
boyfriend you see is not real okay if
you saw a boyfriend who's being
unreasonable with you because you've
been unreasonable in the past now that
boyfriend
exists okay and you can deal you can
relate to that boyfriend and you can fix
him with by fixing your seats okay but
but the other kind of boyfriend the
boyfriend who's mean who's unreasonable
to you not because you've been
unreasonable that boyfriend you can't
you can't there's no meaningful thing
you can do with him cuz he doesn't exist
you can't affect the thing that doesn't
exist you can't throw rocks at a thing
that or shoot a thing that doesn't exist
or or slap a thing that doesn't exist
there not there okay so if you do any of
those things it's going to
fail because the object that you're
acting towards doesn't
exist
okay you are Coring
two-headed purple elephants into the
corner of the
room all
right uh who I pick
on jeffie
[Music]
Sun
cool very very very uh heavy duty Karma
to be here okay so you should be happy